[Music]
so this is a slightly different kind of
film where we're going to be
sense-making the corona virus outbreak
and things are sort of changing day by
day minute by minute and this is a real
sort of task for sense making so in this
we're going to play a few clips from
different people some people have been
on the channel before some people who
are new and looking at sort of the wider
context the challenges to making sense
of it what are the sort of systemic
fragilities and what are the sort of
second-order issues that this is likely
to throw up I mean it feels like it's
almost certain to stress test our
societies like the sense-making and also
health care system and all of the other
systems as well and this is going to be
a live sort of ongoing sense-making
exploration so we're going to obviously
return to this in future days I kind of
feel a little bit kind of frazzled right
now kind of information overload myself
yeah and in these kind of environments I
certainly feel a real sense of
responsibility around like anyone
sharing information in this time I think
there's an extra level of responsibility
and awareness that that certainly I feel
and we feel in in doing this because
anything that we're sharing can have
serious consequences and so we're going
to be really really careful with what
we're saying what we're what we're
sharing while at the same trying time to
hold that the fact that things are
uncertain some of the information seems
to contradict itself there are different
perspectives and that we all need to
upregulate
and to improve our sense making and
discernment as we as we kind of go
through this so we have interviews with
Thomas poyo who wrote an article that
you may have read it it was hugely
popular it's been shared over 24 million
times it's an amazing piece of work of
about 37 pages and as far as I can tell
it's more complete and more well
researched than anything I've seen in
the mainstream media and Thomas isn't a
journalist Thomas's works in tech so
this is going to be another factor as we
look at like
where are the if some of the sense
making organs are being overwhelmed and
not fit for purpose where are the new
sense making people and networks coming
from we're also going to hear from two
people who've been on the channel before
Alex Evans who's a former UK government
adviser and also the creator of the
collective psychology project we're also
going to hear from Josh fields it was on
the channel quite recently talking about
collapse and systems change systems
fragility and we're also going to hear
from Joe Edelman of human systems and
Joe has not been on the channel before
but he is in this sort of wider
sense-making community and is very very
highly regarded and he's got a lot of
really interesting stuff to share so you
mentioned the word frazzled before and
that's certainly what I'm feeling right
now having been delving into lots of
different sources of information and
there's a couple of other concepts we've
talked about in the channel which I
think are really being tested right now
so one of them is sovereignty this
ability to stay connected to ourselves
but also be receptive to the world
another is discernment you know this
huge amount of information and a huge
amount of uncertainty complexity and
chaos really with things changing every
day
you know I've certainly felt that in
myself my both of those things my
sovereignty my connectedness to myself
and then also my discernment especially
this huge almost overwhelm of
information so that and I've also been
reminded you know I think well firstly I
think we're all experiencing that or
pretty much everyone I've spoken to is
experiencing that is something where
we're all experiencing kind of at the
same time and so this this process of
making sense live feels like important
but for me also feels like one of the
only things I feel like I can do right
now it's just kind of do the best job I
can and kind of making sense staying as
centered as I can and being as
discerning as I can as well yeah I think
and it's one of those times where you
can almost feel like the collective
consciousness like everyone is aware of
this everyone is responding in their own
ways and just the blizzard of
sense-making as well just things are
changing hour by hour and minute by
minute and probably even by the time we
upload this in a couple of hours time
things will have changed so this is not
that this is not an attempt to kind of
make sense of what the
current state of affairs is we're going
to direct people to and give some links
to people to follow on Twitter and other
other sense-making
environments that people can kind of
track that stuff given that this is kind
of real-time sense making we would love
to hear from you guys put any sort of
really well researched or really
interesting since making resources into
the comments below we're also opening up
a new thread on the discord channel and
we're looking to to make sense while
being mindful that we don't want to take
resources away from people who are doing
that well elsewhere so if you feel that
there are communities that are doing
this well elsewhere please do get in
touch we've created a new email address
for anyone who feels they've got
something to add to this kind of ongoing
project and we'll bring that up on
screen now so I'm gonna play part of the
interview with Thomas pueyo who wrote
this incredibly viral article that has
been shared over 24 million times in the
last few days you wrote an article that
was incredibly well researched I think
it was about 39 pages in total that has
been very very popular I think I've been
shared over 24 million times now in the
last few days would you just be able to
sort of summarize what do you think is
the main takeaway from that article that
people need to know the number of cases
of coroner virus is exploding the
globally people don't realize that's
happening because this is exponential
which means that at the beginning it's
very slow and suddenly it explodes that
is why most countries have not taking
the measures that they needed to take
the moment to take the measures it's
when it's here it's not only it's here
at that point the outbreak has already
exploded so what you need to show other
of the article explain what's going to
happen which is if you don't do anything
the cases are gonna explode once they
explode they're going to overrun the
healthcare system once they do the
mortality rate of the coroner others
will explode probably up to 10x 10 times
higher mortality
Thomas can I ask your your background
because I understand you're not in the
media or not a journal
how long do I have to meet you two right
and what's your background for doing
this so I had spent before I wrote it I
had spent around two weeks researching
this around for four to five hours a day
and I think your underlying question is
why should people listen to me and I
think the answer is they shouldn't they
shouldn't listen to me I I am NOT going
to be down knowledge I just I'm not a
biologist what I've done is gather all
the research from all these different
places and put it in one place so people
can understand it you should judge the
article based on the data and the
arguments and sources not on the fact
that it's me it so happens that I have a
couple of background elements that have
helped me put this together I'm an
engineer I have two masters of science
so I'm very very close to all things
data and analysis and statistics I
worked as a consultant where I had to
get into account in companies and
understand them within two to three
weeks so I'm very I have experience
going deep into understanding a problem
very very quickly I also created some
very altercations that exploded to up to
20 million users so I am acquainted with
the analytics of virality I think these
are some of the reasons why I was able
to put these two together but people
shouldn't see me as the person making
the arguments but rather making the
Assembly of the arguments and so we talk
a lot on on this channel we look very
closely at sense making what are the
failures and sense making and especially
about how do we get better how do we up
regulate our discernment and our sense
making and it's really interesting that
you seem to be doing something that so
far the mainstream media hasn't done to
that level why do you think that is
the media and and politicians and and
and I care about both but I came more
about politicians I think I think one of
the key mental frameworks that most
people are lack is exponential growth
the the my job I didn't mention that in
but in my job both in the viral
applications but but in tech in general
you're going for exponential growth and
you understand the mechanics of
experience for growth so when you see
that something is growing at 20% or 30%
day over day you freak out you're you're
super happy if it's your product or
you're super super super scared if it's
a virus but because you understand
what's gonna happen in a week two weeks
three weeks three months four months so
I think that's what that's one of the
key issues why people didn't understand
what was going to happen there's also an
issue of connecting the dots here
because it's not just one part this is a
puzzle and you need to put it together
and most journalists especially when
they're covering news they are not
trained to put all the pieces together
we're seeing a lot of systemic
fragilities in various different areas
and one of them is the ability to make
sense of the crisis and I think one of
the things that's required is for people
to to improve their discernment to step
up and potentially alternatives to some
of the failing systems are emerging and
I would put you in that bracket as
someone who seems to be making sense of
the outbreak better than most if not all
in the mainstream media sense that that
people are having to step up here we are
in a perfect example of new information
coming to society
it reminds me for example what happened
with uh with drugs heads or the Trump
election in 2016 where it took everybody
the back nobody knew how to interpret
that situation right and so suddenly
there's these new information in the
system and and and the system just
doesn't know how to cope with it and so
it tries to digest it so the question
becomes when you have these this doesn't
happen frequently by the way
but but when it happens what is the best
process to to process this information
as quickly as possible and I would say
what is happening today is the right way
to do it yeah this film is not to
concentrate on sort of the logistics of
the virus like the transmission rates or
the ways of protecting ourselves and all
of that that's really available
elsewhere
I've highly recommend the Joe Rogan
podcast and the Sam Harris podcast
recently with experts in the field and
it's really interesting to see how these
long-form podcasts do feel like they're
coming into their own when there's an
there's a very complex situation I'll
just add to that as well as you're
talking about it what strikes me is that
another thing that the traditional news
outlets struggle to do is cooperate in
the same way that that people are
cooperating online where it's
decentralized it's not a competition
it's about people finding and sharing
the best information and that builds on
itself in a very decentralized way as
opposed to we've got the scoop and we
better we better hold on to this
completely different model we're gonna
play a very short clip now from the Sam
Harris podcast with a mesh adelgid from
the Johns Hopkins University it's still
an enormous number of people dead from
this virus yeah I think it is going to
be more than people will imagine but
will it be cataclysmic I don't think
that's that's the case the highest flu
death rate we have I think outside of a
pandemic is 80,000 and 2017 to 2018 so
this is magnitude higher than that and I
do think it's gonna be disruptive and
bad but I think that what I'm worried
about is that people's actions and
reactions and and and panic will
actually make things worse and and
really lead to this kind of cascading
effect where where hospitals can't
operate where where there is widespread
social chaos going on and that's why
what really worries me more than the
virus itself yeah so that clip really
leads into what most of the rest of this
is going to be about which is the
second-order consequences the systemic
fragility and how this might play out
I'm going to start with the the way that
different countries are responding to
this
in particular the UK seems to be taking
and again this is changing kind of alibi
our like the UK has has has changed
position quite significantly even in the
last couple of days even today but the U
the UK had decided on a very different
path
to many other countries so Italy went
into lockdown China went into lockdown
but that seems to be what Spain is doing
and what most of the other European
countries are doing the UK decided on a
course of what they're calling herd
immunity and this is why this is really
interesting is that the UK one of the
most senior advisors in the UK is a guy
called Dominic Cummings and Dominic
Cummings is incredibly well versed in
complexity theory in some of the kind of
topics that we've talked about on the
channel and a lot of people who are kind
of involved in making sense in this sort
of sense making community would be
worked very well aware of and Cummings
if you look at his blog he kind of
details all of these like he's a first
principles thinker
he's very allergic to doing what
everyone else is doing he's very
allergic to the status quo and so it's
interesting that he's chosen or we
assume that he's heavily involved in
this decision by the UK government to
the nature of the British political
system if you're kind of watching from
from the US when is much more
centralized than the US and power is
very concentrated on the prime minister
and very concentrated in the Prime
Minister's advisor in this case he's
very very powerful in the UK and despite
the huge pressure to change course at
the moment the UK looks to be taking a
different step and I talked to Alex
Evans who as I said he used to work in
the British government about this and
also Josh fields they're talking about
something called herd immunity they're
assuming that most people will get the
virus so they're wanting to to manage
the numbers and and once once they're
calculating that 60 percent of people
have developed immunity then there will
be some immunity in the population but I
think that also depends on one key
unknown or that maybe unknown is whether
immunity develops and if immunity
doesn't develop then that's a not only a
high-risk strategy it's actually
potentially a really suicidal strategy
yeah so let me just dump out a little
bit Harrod immunity is really the you
kid this is the second principle of why
UK government policy is different
Harrod immunity is basically saying look
people are gonna get the virus anyway we
should let people get said virus but
ensure that it is mainly law grasp risk
groups law risk categories who end up
getting the virus and what will this do
well the idea hypothesis is they get the
virus they recover from the virus and in
so doing they actually build immunity to
the virus and so they don't become
future carriers of said virus now why
might this be a wise strategy because in
other words it's basically saying let's
give more of the population in this
infection right why might this be wise I
think part of the thinking behind is if
you go to China or Italy people are in
quarantine these people aren't actually
building immunity right because they're
not a lot of them are not actually
picking up the virus it's just a self
self as a it's a precautious measure to
stop the spread know if the virus is is
doubling in size every four days in
terms of the number of people it's
affecting that quarantine is an
excellent way to stop that spread but it
doesn't do much for future immunity and
so I think part of the rationale behind
this is if you give Loras groups more of
the infection we build the immunity over
time and so we won't need interventions
like quarantine six twelve months in the
future and China and Italy
what happens if everybody starts to come
out on the streets again and then
suddenly there's another via there's
another outbreak of the virus they have
to go back to the quarantine whereas if
our population become could become more
resistant that could be hypothetically a
good thing no this is extremely this is
a high-risk high-reward strategy because
what it basically confers Azur suggests
is we can actually build 30-minute herd
immunity right i think that's
problematic for two reasons the first
there is absolutely fuck-all evidence
that we can there is an implicit
assumption from
biologist this is what tends to happen
and which by the way I'd really like to
see open sourced we're basing our
surrender to Herod immunity on models we
don't understand or have not seen but
the second is the presupposition that we
can actually build build immunity so is
really said suggests or hopes that our
immune systems are strong enough to do
that but our local our our modern world
with toxins and pollution and the
we eat suggests that immune systems
aren't quite now what the or they once
were and so it's a big risk it's a hell
of a big risk and I'd love to see things
open sourced to really know why the
rationale for this but just such a bit
just to give a summary then the U key is
different in two ways we're noting we're
not encouraging social social isolation
because of behavioral psychology and
because of herd immunity both of those
things are I on two major asam two major
assumptions one is capacity to predict
and the capacity to build immunity I
think we need to see more evidence as to
why those are fear clear assumptions to
make yeah and it's interesting there was
a letter today or a series of letters to
the times from very senior medical
people making exactly those points that
we need to see the models we need to
understand why the government is taking
these decisions and while I agree with
you I also wonder if there's a second
factor involved or another factor
involved which is that we're very we're
not very good at talking about risk
especially in the media the media is
generally very good at to sell papers
that sort of over at overstating risks
so I think the reason they haven't done
this so far is that once you start once
you start having a really honest
conversation about the UK strategy the
next question that will come back from
journalists is so are you saying that
you're basically encouraging people to
get the virus are you saying that you
are going to wilfully allow people to
die because of this virus and the answer
to those is going to be
because that is the strategy that the UK
is has chosen but that's not a strategy
that can be reported well in the media
you can see the headlines now governor
says people must die so that is I think
another failure condition of this of the
response to the virus is that with we're
terrible at understanding and talking
about risk and we're terrible about
being able to communicate that without
scare mongering and that's that's
another systemic fragility that I think
is being shown up with the with what's
going on at the moment one one if if we
were to speak in really crude terms as
to what parrot immunity actually means
in practice it's really us taking age or
the government taking agency or bruh how
much it Thai treats the virus if
instantly says we're gonna load the
virus get to the Symone when we think
it's reached our our peak ie when we
think our health care resources can no
longer handle more we will titrate it
and we'll close schools and we'll lead
to social isolation but really if you
can read between the lines of what that
means it is really saying like we're
gonna load there to know now we're gonna
stop death we're gonna load death no
we're gonna stop death and I think that
is yeah I'm politically unfeasible on
the media aspect um I think you're right
that it becomes difficult for the
government to be upfront about the
dilemmas and trade-offs that any
government has to navigate in this kind
of an issue because as you say the media
will often you know go into kind of
gotcha
mode and aim to kind of embarrass the
government or go for the most
sensational angle possible I mean it's
not unlike the Facebook algorithm which
will push content at us that's the most
triggering or outraging or scary content
because they know that that's the most
effective way of monetizing our
attention and of course the media have
many of the same incentives in place so
I mean I think that you know one of the
interesting things in all of this is
that you know we are all speculating
about what is the top-down strategy from
government here but also if we focus on
the things that are if you like within
our own circle of control there is this
whole other aspect which is the
bottom-up response to it which is both
about people's own decisions in their
everyday lives whether they observe
social distancing protocol
or just assumed well I'll be fine it
doesn't matter if I get it whether
they're engaging in panic buying or
leaving goods for others and so on and
so there's that aspect and also I think
we're seeing this weekend in particular
a huge amount of self organizing
happening in communities to build Street
and neighborhood level resilience in a
way that's really encouraging and I
think you know however it plays out
however the government's strategy pans
out over time this is stuff that can
only be a good thing so I think there's
if you like two sides to the resilient
story here I just wanted to recap the
proviso in that because it is really
really important that the assumption of
the herd immunity strategy like we're
not advocating one way or another we're
trying to make sense of different
conflicting narratives and conflicting
perspectives without trying to collapse
into any one of them but the the
important thing here is that the British
government's assumption about herd
immunity relies on the fact that once
someone has had the virus they develop
immunity and that is an assumption and
if that's not the case then what the UK
is thinking of doing becomes infinitely
more dangerous in fact very very
dangerous so I just want to kind of put
a flag in that that's something you need
we need to watch out for and sort of
more information onto whether that's the
case and the other thing that it's worth
flagging up again was mentioned in those
clips is this is really challenging to
mainstream media sense making because
we're it's very very difficult to talk
about risk in a sane sensible way when
sensationalism rules and you can just
see that the questions that would be
asked at the press conference is the
potential newspaper headlines where the
question is okay you're pursuing a herd
immunity strategy mr. Boris Johnson so
are you saying that you want people to
get the virus are you saying that people
that you are going to pursue a strategy
that means more people will die and then
you end up with potentially newspaper
headlines that say government kills the
elderly or something like that because
we can't talk about systemic risk we
can't talk about the balance of risks
sensibly in a
sensationalist media environment and
that's another of the sort of systemic
fragilities that we're seeing being kind
of flagged up here and this is something
that I also talked about with some of
the interviewees
you've just put out a piece called the
corona crisis and designing better
social systems and you say right at the
beginning of it that this corona crisis
only an economic crash connected to it
reveals yet again how Western
institutions and social systems are
failing you want to expand on that what
are you seeing already that has led you
to conclude that yeah sure I think
there's it's a it's a lot so one thing
that's failing is the media and in
general there's a feeling that the US
and the UK have suffered a kind of decay
where people trust the government less
than they used to where the government
kind of deserves less trust than it used
to deserve for a few of us that are
following the right accounts on Twitter
we've actually been in a better position
to make sense of the crisis but at the
same time there's massive misinformation
and confusion going on very little
ability to cohere around that if you
look at what's trending and the tweets
that are going the most viral these are
not actually the ones that have the best
information content so we see breakdown
in media we see a breakdown in political
systems what do you think about the
crisis in sense making that we're seeing
now so I've been writing about this for
a couple of years been thinking about it
a hail of the law and when we think
about sense making think about it in two
ways the first is the information that
is coming into our environment from our
environment and also our capacity to
discern that information from that
environment and so if you look at the
first one this exponential increase in
misinformation this information in fake
news means that as sense-making
organisms we're struggling to actually
know what what information we can
actually trust okay and so I don't know
if you've seen with this coronavirus
stuff you've got the happy Debbie's on
one side good basically going this is
all some sort of conspiracy theory by
the government and it's all about love
and if your
panicking your your lower chakra energy
is wherever they want to say and then
there's there's a bolts most likely
disseminating bad information in order
to increase systemic instability and so
the information ecology is a
mess it's it's a mess and so if
we're trying to actually get behind a
consistent narrative as to what to do
and they're all these competing claims
in social media
it becomes hell of a hard to sense make
I think part of that is linked to we've
lost trust in our institutions we've
lost trust in our em epistemological
authorities and that's problematic if we
want to create a coherent cohesive
response the other problem is and this
is going to go to the second point which
is our ability to actually take in that
information because we're so overwhelmed
with anxiety and mental health issues
because our concentration capacities are
actually decreasing our ability to make
discerning and sovereign decisions about
what is good information and what is bad
information is also compromised so you
have this juxtaposition of shifty
information and shetty capacity to
handle that information in the presence
of exponential complexity it's it's
highly problematic and I think part of
the issue with that man yes there's an
epistemological crisis because we're not
trusting I think part of the reason
we're not trusting is because this lack
of trust that's disseminating right
but why how did we get to a position of
a lack of truth in the first place
and I think part of it is we in the West
the the the Herald's and this and the
creators of the cultures of science and
technology and engineering ie
truth based paradigms we ourselves have
actually taken on more a face over truth
culture than a truth over face culture
and so this we've normalized deceit in
our culture but because it's so
normalized people don't think it's
actually a problem
you had exponential technology to that
cultural adaptation of the seal the
truth I in that cultural adaptation a
little bit more just what you mean by
that face over truth yeah so when when
you look at em a lot of Asian cultures
Asian cultures tend to put their
family's reputation or their their and
their external projection to the world
over and above what is actually true so
a lot of people have summarized this as
Western culture is more of a guilt based
culture and Eastern culture and more of
a shame based culture in the social
shame or what people think of you is the
primary driver of behavior in the eat in
the East there on the west it's like
individual conscience and your own yeah
being able to square your own actions
with your own in a truth and and more of
the Christian tradition is more on the
individual and that what you're saying
and I think I've heard a few other
people say as well as like in the social
media age and in the in the the
environment that we've created for
ourselves now it's much more in the West
about what where people think of
ourselves and less about the actual
behavior yeah we've I think the point
that I'm trying to make here is that
we've created the cult rule for that
we've created the cultural container
that is just right for misinformation
disinformation and fake news because our
culture doesn't actually no longer
actually holds truths to be one of its
highest virtues or values instead it
holds that this kind of like this
narcissistic co-optation
and more to be more significant and more
important and then we have the issue of
systemic fragility I think we're all
realizing that there's going to be many
second and third-order consequences of
this as it kind of cascades through the
system and that's something that I
talked to both Josh and to Joe about how
do you see this playing out sort of in
the in the I guess medium term in terms
of the systemic fragilities
hmmm I mean I think we're we're probably
in for a pretty bad economic downturn
and I think what's happening is it's
actually very promising promising and
exciting we're seeing a deal Ajith
imitation of certain ways of doing
things and then a possible legitimate
itemization of other newer ways of doing
things and I think this is how political
change happens more generally like if we
look at transitions from monarchies to
representative democracies it's often
assumed that there's some kind of like
revolution and this is the main moment
that it happens but if you look at the
American Revolution for instance the
people that kind of took over during the
American Revolution were actually
already running things in the colonies
and they had a different way of
operating citizens assemblies and things
like that so they had they developed
legitimacy under the radar below the
level of the monarchy and the official
representatives of the King and so by
the time they wanted to have an American
Revolution they'd kind of proven
themselves as a new way of operating and
improving themselves in a series of
crises before the kind of big crisis at
the American Revolution and I think this
is how this is the more more common way
that political change happens and we can
see it happening right now as the CDC
you know some governmental actors become
dita legitimize the way that they do
things clearly isn't working for the
people and new actors that maybe have no
relationship to government are looking
very responsible and very capable and I
think what we need to do right now is we
need to do our best to make sure that
the capable looking actors are also
promising in terms of new social
mechanisms in terms of new political
mechanisms we wouldn't want this to go
into a moment where we develop a more
authoritarian or even fascist
existent because that works we we need
to make sure that we have some kind of
hopefully sort of quasi democratic
optimistic new systems that are seen to
be performing well in the crisis and are
you seeing anything any sort of real
world networks or projects that are kind
of that are happening now that are
giving you hope or that you're paying
attention to yes absolutely I think I
see many communities I see that there's
a kind of a techno hippie scene which i
think is doing great work it's kind of
like the Burning Man kind of that area I
see a lot of really talented nerdy
people also the rationalists the
effective altruists these people seem to
be responding rapidly organizing doing
better than the meta modernists better
than a lot of the political theorists I
think what's one kind of group that's
shining right now is the kinds of people
who have 60 meetups around the world
like this kind of group and it may be
that they've been doing I don't know
circling or yeah I don't know
responsible charity stuff in the past
but now they're ready to coordinate and
do something more immediate more useful
so I think I think we're seeing a lot of
these kinds of global community global
glocal communities are having a moment
to shine I think we all have a sense
that there's going to be huge unintended
consequences coming out of this that
we're not really aware of yet I was with
a family member yesterday who is in
recovery from alcoholism and I was just
thinking this person has a Hugh has
quite a lot of so
all events that they're going to they're
involved in going to recovery meetings
if those sort of things shut down like
these unintended consequences I know
that this person will relapse for
example then we've got people who and
like and we know for example that we're
such social creatures that we need we
actually need human connection like
social isolation is an actual torture
Sarris individual isolation in well they
call it in jail not social isolation
confinement so we know that solitary
confinement in jail is actually a
torture because we are the kind of
creatures that need to meet to connect
to align our stories to and if we don't
if we don't do that we we tend to
atrophy so are you worried about what
that might mean sort of longer term or
medium term yeah I think you're
absolutely right the data shows that
loneliness is actually as bad for life
expectancy as smoking 15 or 20
cigarettes a day and I think as you say
this is going to be one of the
consequences of consequences if you like
of the corona virus outbreak and I think
one of the particularly cruel twists of
this is that the people some of the most
vulnerable people to coronavirus like
elderly people who are the ones who will
really need to stay home are often
communities among whom loneliness is
spiking in the first place there you
have this added twist that no they won't
be able to see the grandchildren but
also they won't be able to have the kind
of you know day-to-day so-called weak
ties contact with people like you know
someone at the GP surgery someone at the
post office someone in the supermarket
those sort of little day-to-day
interactions that make you feel at least
connected in your community so the
emotional toll of all of this is going
to be really hard you can have lots of
people either sick or just isolating for
their own protection and feeling bored
lonely anxious and then as the as the
epidemic moves on there will also be
grief to contend with because you know
we'll start to see deaths and I think
the question of what sort of support
mechanisms we can get in place while
obviously observing social distancing
protocols a really important one
one of their really encouraging things
that is happening this weekend is that
I'm seeing lots and lots of things on
Twitter where people are going out into
their own communities just you know now
before the tsunami hit to reach out and
just get their neighbors contact details
and for example just set up a
street-level whatsapp group which can be
on the one hand a way for people to kind
of check in and stay up with news and
share content and just sort of feel
connected but also that's going to be a
way of coordinating community self-help
so that if there's people that you know
need prescriptions or supermarket shops
picking up or maybe they need cooking
for all their dogs walking that sort of
stuff can self-organize and just emerge
very quickly but it is important that
you know the bandwidth the kind of the
social network connections are in place
on whatsapp or on a Facebook group or
whatever it may be before things get
really difficult so that's a great
concrete thing that all of us can get on
with this weekend so I really want to
emphasize this is live sense making a
lot of this as provisional could change
sort of in the next hour even by the
time maybe we put this out and we want
to yeah we want to ramp up our ability
to kind of make sense and relay accurate
information as best as possible so do
put kind of useful links useful
information in the in the comments below
and as I said we've created a new thread
in the discord that will be in we're
gonna put all of the links and all of
the relevant kind of people to follow on
Twitter and places to go for good sense
making into the show notes so do look at
that do if you are someone who's been
following this you have high discernment
high sovereignty anything that you can
contribute we'd love to hear from you at
this email address here and we'll be
updating this regularly will of course
be putting out more films and more
information as we get it so thank you
for watching and see you see
you